<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Technical-Architecture on Athan Dial - Portfolio</title>
    <link>https://athan-dial.github.io/tags/technical-architecture/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Technical-Architecture on Athan Dial - Portfolio</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 15 Jan 2026 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://athan-dial.github.io/tags/technical-architecture/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Reducing Data Pipeline Latency to Enable Real-Time Decision Loops</title>
      <link>https://athan-dial.github.io/case-studies/reducing-pipeline-latency-decision-velocity/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 15 Jan 2026 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://athan-dial.github.io/case-studies/reducing-pipeline-latency-decision-velocity/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;context&#34;&gt;Context&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Business teams were making critical decisions on data that was 2-3 days old, causing them to miss market opportunities and react to problems rather than prevent them. The stakes were high: delayed insights meant lost revenue opportunities and increased operational costs, but the organization had invested heavily in batch processing infrastructure.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This work lived in the core data platform that served analytics teams, operations teams, and executive dashboards across the organization. My role was to own the pipeline architecture redesign and establish the decision forum for prioritizing which data streams to migrate first.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Standardizing Montai&#39;s App Ecosystem with R Shiny</title>
      <link>https://athan-dial.github.io/case-studies/shiny-framework-standardization-montai/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Jun 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://athan-dial.github.io/case-studies/shiny-framework-standardization-montai/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;context&#34;&gt;Context&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;By mid-2024, Montai&amp;rsquo;s internal web app landscape had fragmented. Different engineers built tools in their preferred frameworks — Python Streamlit, Python Dash, R Shiny, Jupyter notebooks — creating a sprawling ecosystem with inconsistent UX and duplicated effort. For a small data team (~5-6 people), this fragmentation imposed hidden costs: context-switching overhead, maintenance burden, and harder onboarding.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Facts:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;2024: Growing need for internal web apps (compound selection, data visualization, report generation)&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Problem: Different engineers using different frameworks (Python Streamlit/Dash, R Shiny, Jupyter notebooks)&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Pain: Inconsistent UX, duplicated effort, hard to maintain, context-switching cost&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Stakes: Small team (~5-6 people) needed velocity + consistency&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Technical leadership was needed to converge on a single approach. The challenge: balance team skills, deployment infrastructure, and use case requirements — while avoiding the trap of &amp;ldquo;one size fits all&amp;rdquo; dogma that ignores practical constraints.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
